Guide to the Leonard Weinglass Papers TAM.584
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Leonard Weinglass Papers
1950s-2011
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Smith, Michael Steven, 1942-
Weinglass, Leonard
TAM.584
58.75 Linear Feet in 63 boxes.
5.2 Gigabytes on 3 optical discs.
Leonard Irving Weinglass (1933--2011) was a U.S. criminal defense lawyer and constitutional law advocate who championed a number of liberal and radical causes. He served as co-chairman of the international committee of the National Lawyers Guild. Along with attorney William Kunstler, Weinglass represented the Chicago Seven in their 1968 trial. He also participated in the defense of Daniel Ellsberg and Anthony Russo, who were charged with leaking the Pentagon Papers and whose trial ended in a dismissal of all charges. In 1970, he represented and won the acquittal of Angela Davis who was charged with participation in the abduction and murder of a local judge. Weinglass was the lead defense attorney for Mumia Abu-Jamal for several years. In 1995, he authored a book about Abu-Jamal's case entitled Race for Justice: Mumia Abu Jamal's Fight Against the Death Penalty. The unprocessed Leonard Weinglass Papers contain case files and related material for many famous legal struggles, such as the Pentagon Papers, Mumia Abu-Jamal, and the Chicago Seven, as well as other cases, including those of Kurt Alan Stand and Susan Komarisuk. Weinglass's speaking engagements and research files also make up a significant part of the collection. Aside from paper records, the collection contains audio-visual materials and artwork.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Michael and Deborah Smith in 2011. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2011.079, 2011.121, 2019.069, and 2019.146.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. Materials are in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Leonard Irving Weinglass (August 27, 1933--March 23, 2011) graduated from Yale Law School in 1958 and was a U.S. criminal defense lawyer and constitutional law advocate who championed a number of liberal and radical causes. An expert in constitutional law, he served as co-chairman of the international committee of the National Lawyers Guild. Along with attorney William Kunstler, Weinglass represented the Chicago 7 in their 1968 trial. He also participated in the defense of Daniel Ellsberg and Anthony Russo, who were charged with leaking the Pentagon Papers and whose trial ended in a dismissal of all charges. In 1970, he represented and won the acquittal of Angela Davis who was charged with participation in the abduction and murder of a local judge. Weinglass was the lead defense attorney for Mumia Abu-Jamal for several years. In 1995, he authored a book about Abu-Jamal's case entitled Race for Justice: Mumia Abu Jamal's Fight Against the Death Penalty.
Other prominent clients included Kathy Boudin, a member of the Weather Underground charged with felony murder for her participation in an armed robbery; anti-war activist Ron Kaufman; Bill and Emily Harris (of the SLA) and Jimi Simmons, among others. In 1972, Weinglass took on the defense of John Sinclair, Chairman of the White Panther Party in Detroit, Michigan. The case became United States v. U.S. District Court, 407 U.S. 297 (1972) on appeal to the United States Supreme Court, a landmark decision prohibiting the government's use of electronic surveillance without a warrant. In 1985, Weinglass successfully defended Stephen Bingham, an attorney accused of smuggling a handgun to George Jackson in San Quentin Prison setting off an escape attempt that resulted in the death of Jackson, two other inmates, and three prison guards. Weinglass was the lead appellate attorney for the Cuban Five from 2002 until his death in 2011.
Scope and Contents
The Leonard Weinglass Papers contain case files and related material for many famous legal struggles, such as the Pentagon Papers, Mumia Abu-Jamal, and the Chicago Seven, as well as other cases, including those of Kurt Alan Stand and Susan Komarisuk. Weinglass's speaking engagements (including regarding the case of Daniel Ellsberg) and research files also make up a significant part of the collection. Aside from paper records, the collection contains audio-visual materials, born-digital materials, and artwork.
Separated Materials
One linear foot of books was separated to the Tamiment Library collection for cataloging.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Freedom of information -- Government policy -- United States.; Legal documents.; Legal correspondence.; Legal files.; Speeches.; Research (document genres).; Chicago Seven Trial, Chicago, Ill., 1969-1970.; Lawyers -- Political activity -- United States.; Constitutional law -- United States -- Cases; Civil rights -- United States.; Trials (Political crimes and offenses) -- United States.; Weinglass, Leonard; Smith, Michael Steven, 1942-; Ellsberg, Daniel.; Abu-Jamal, Mumia; National Lawyers Guild; Komisaruk, Susan Alexis; Davis, Angela Y. (Angela Yvonne), 1944-; Stand, Kurt Alan
- Files on Individuals (correspondence, clippings, etc.) and Contempt of Court Decision (1995), 1990s-2000s; 381957 (Box 1)
- Novaspes Records (including board minutes), 1996-2001; 381958 (Box 2)
- U.S. v. Susan Alexis Komisaruk, 1987-1989; 381959 (Box 3)
- Research Files for Article on Contempt of Court, 1970s-1990s; 381960 (Box 4)
- Files on Individuals (correspondence, clippings, etc.) and Organizations (especially anti-death penalty groups), 1990s-2000s; 382058 (Box 5)
- U.S. v. Filiberto Ojeda Rios, et al, 1989-1990; 382059 (Box 6)
- Speaking Materials Research: Crime, Prisons, Law, and Government, 1970s-2000s; 382060 (Box 7)
- Travel, 2006-2007; 382061 (Box 8)
- U.S. v. Susan Alexis Komisaruk and Research Files on Juries, 1960s-1970s, 1987-1989; 382062 (Box 9)
- Research Files on Juries, 4 West 21st Street (NYC) Construction (2005), and Diane Downey/Daniel Ligget Case, 1960s-1970s, 2005; 382063 (Box 10)
- Film and Video of "Chicago Seven" (Pacific Street Films), undated; 382064 (Box 11)
- Jacques Loussier v. Universal Music Group ("Eminem Case"), William Guerrero, et al v. Jerome Terrace, et al ("Feldman Case"), Craig Winchell Parole, and Files on Individuals (correspondence, clippings, etc.), 1970s-2009; 382065 (Box 12)
- Files on Individuals (correspondence, clippings, etc.), Real Estate Records, and Discovery: FBI Files on Anti-World Bank and International Monetary Fund (IMF) Protests, 1980s-2000s; 382066 (Box 13)
- Alliance for Global Justice, et al v. District of Columbia, et al; Discovery: FBI Files on Anti-World Bank and International Monetary Fund (IMF) Protests; and Death Penalty, 1970s-2000s; 382067 (Box 14)
- International Law, the Necessity Defense, Peru Case, Criminal Law Reporter, and Student Papers, 1980s-2000s; 382069 (Box 15)
- Research Files on Juries and Student Papers, 1970s; 382070 (Box 16)
- Research Files on Juries, Student Papers, and Various Cases Ordered by Subject, 1970s-2003; 382071 (Box 17)
- Prisoners' Correspondence, Human Trafficking, California v. William Taylor Harris and Emily Montague Harris, FBI Files on Weinglass, and Various Manuscripts and Court Transcripts, 1970s-2008; 382072 (Box 18)
- Speaking Materials; U.S. v. Gerardo Hernandez, et al; "Rights on the Line" Program (on Patriot Act and Other Anti-Terrorism Measures); and General Legal Files, 1970s-2000s; 382073 (Box 19)
- U.S. v. Alexander Sanchez, Mammilla Cemetery Case (Jerusalem), New York v. Everton McKenzie, Newark Water Case, Melissa Roxas Case (Philippines), and Other Recent Cases and General Legal Files, 1990s-2000s; 382074 (Box 20)
- U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand, California v. Angela Y. Davis and Ruchell Magee, and Files on Courtroom Techniques, 1970s-late 1990s; 382076 (Box 21)
- U.S. v. Anthony Joseph Russo and Daniel Ellsberg, U.S. v. Victor Gerena, et al, Judicial Misconduct, Flag Burning, and Iran-Contra, early 1970s-late 1980s; 382077 (Box 22)
- U.S. v. Anthony Joseph Russo and Daniel Ellsberg, U.S. v. Ronald Kaufman, Flag Burning, and Subject Files: U.S. Presidents, Rights of the Accused, Punishment/Prisons, Civil Liberties, U.S. War Crimes, Prosecutors, and Israel, 1970s-2000s; 382092 (Box 23)
- Jury Nullification and Subject Files: Federal Courts/Supreme Courts, Law Enforcement, the Rich, Poverty, the Economy, Race, the Military, and Cuba, 1970s-1980s, 2000s; 382093 (Box 24)
- Jury Nullification, Necessity Defense, and Speaking Files (including text of speeches), 1970s-2000s; 382094 (Box 25)
- Speaking Files (including text of speeches), 1970-2011; 382095 (Box 26)
- Speaking Files: Supportive Materials (includes files on human rights, torture, incarceration, and the Patriot Act) [folder level inventory inside box), 1990s-2000s; 382096 (Box 27)
- Speaking Files: Supportive Materials (includes files on foreign affairs, Israel, and various "personalities") [folder level inventory inside box]; Chicago Conspiracy Trial; Conference on Cuba; and Ongoing Cases, 1970s-late 2000s; 382097 (Box 28)
- Legal Research on Juries, Center for Human Rights and Constitutional Law v. National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency, National Aeronautics and Space Administration and Other Recent Cases, 1970s-2011; 382107 (Box 29)
- Legal Research on Juries, 1970s-1980s; 382108 (Box 30)
- U.S. v. Victor Gerena, et al and Mumia Abu-Jamal Publicity, 1980s-1990s; 382109 (Box 31)
- Mumia Abu-Jamal Publicity and Class Action Lawsuit vs. International Medical Research and Novaspes, 1990s-2000s; 382110 (Box 32)
- Class Action Lawsuit vs. International Medical Research and Novaspes (including settlement and bankruptcy), Mumia Abu-Jamal, Sam Rosenwein Oral History, and Several Unlabeled Videos, 1989-2000s; 382111 (Box 33)
- Dave Dellinger, Bloom v. Cochran, Wang Wu Case, Daniel Gross Case, Gerry Civin v. Reads Associates, et al, Speaking Materials, U.S. v. Anthony Joseph Russo and Daniel Ellsberg, and California v. William Taylor Harris and Emily Montague Harris, 1960s-early 2000s; 382112 (Box 34)
- "Finished Cases, 2000-2001" (folder inventory on top of the box), Bruderhof Material relating to Mumia Abu-Jamal, and U.S. v. Victor Manuel Gerena, et al, 1980s-early 2000s; 382115 (Box 35)
- U.S. v. Victor Manuel Gerena, et al, Correspondence and Meetings with Mumia Abu-Jamal, Family Correspondence and Writings, and Kathy Boudin, 1960s-1990s; 382116 (Box 36)
- Correspondence and Meetings with Mumia Abu-Jamal, Family Correspondence and Writings, Khader Musa Hamide and Michel Ibrahim Shehadeh Case, Palestine, and U.S. v. Ruben Campa, et al, 1960s-2000s; 382117 (Box 37)
- U.S. v. Ruben Campa, et al and Class Action Lawsuit vs. International Medical Research and Novaspes, 1990s-early 2000s; 382118 (Box 38)
- Audio Cassettes (mostly speeches and lectures by Weinglass and others) and VHS Tapes and DVDs (mostly of Weinglass Speeches or regarding Mumia Abu-Jamal), circa 1980s-1990s; 382125 (Box 39)
- Air Force Records and Miscellaneous General Files, 1970, 1980s-2010; 438146 (Box 40)
- Recent General and Speaking Files; Chicago Trial and Related Material, 1960s-2010; 438147 (Box 41)
- Chicago Trial and Related Material; U.S. v. Anthony Joseph Russo and Daniel Ellsberg; Vietnam and the United States, 1960s-1970s; 438150 (Box 42)
- U.S. v. Anthony Joseph Russo and Daniel Ellsberg; Vietnam and the United States; U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand, 1960s-2000s; 438151 (Box 43)
- U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand, late 1990s-2000s; 438152 (Box 44)
- Posters, Photographs, and Framed Artwork, 382126 (Box 45)
- Phonograph Record of Chicago Conspiracy Trial Play, Posters, Photographs, and Framed Artwork, 382914 (Box 46)
- U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand, late 1990s-2000s; 438153 (Box 47)
- U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand (Stand Remand #3), late 1990s-2000s; 438154 (Box 48)
- U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand (Stand Remand #1), late 1990s-2000s; 438155 (Box 49)
- U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand; U.S. v. Ahmed Omar Abu Ali [Folder level inventory inside box], late 1990s-2000s; 438156 (Box 50)
- U.S. v. Ahmed Omar Abu Ali [Folder level inventory inside previous box]; Association of Professional Flight Attendants, 2000s; 438157 (Box 51)
- Association of Professional Flight Attendants, 2000s; 438159 (Box 52)
- Association of Professional Flight Attendants and Cooper, et al. v. TWA Airlines, et al. (includes CD-ROM), 2000s; 438160 (Box 53)
- LA 8, 1980s-1990s; 438163 (Box 54)
- LA 8 and U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand (Stand Remand #2), 1980s-2000s; 438164 (Box 55)
- U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand (Stand Remand #2) and Speaking Files: Supportive Materials, 1970s-2000s; 438166 (Box 56)
- Speaking Files: Supportive Materials, Class Action Lawsuit vs. International Medical Research and Novaspes, Teaching Materials, and Harvey/Klein and Texfel, 1970s-2000s; 438167 (Box 57)
- Teaching Materials (primarily USC Criminal Trial Advocacy class); Notes re: Pentagon Papers Case; USA v. Anthony Joseph Russo, et al.; Select Portions of Legal Texts on Topics such as Cross Examination, Closing Argument; and Loose Pages Involving Various Cases, 1969-1982; 444734 (Box 58)
- Teaching Materials; Personal: Speeches, Memorabilia, Photographs, Publicity, Travel; and Material re: Mumia Abu-Jamal, Phil Berrigan, Alger Hiss and others, 1970s-2000s; 444850 (Box 59)
- Personal: Speaking Engagements, Photographs, Memorabilia, Publicity, Travel, Speaking Materials, 1976-1999; 444851 (Box 60)
- Oversized Framed Work of Art (in need of custom box), 382915 (Box 61)
- Subject Files, Correspondence, U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand, 2002-2007 (Box 62)
- New Jersey Air National Guard Materials, Subject Files, Memorial Materials, 1954-2011 (Box 63)
  - Ricardo Alarcón Statement on Leonard Weinglass, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_584_ER_1)
  - Leonard Weinglass Interview with Miguel Álvarez, 2004 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_584_ER_2)
  - Leonard Weinglass Memorial Event, 2011-05-13 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_584_ER_4)